<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Live-Coding | RumbleSan Heavy Noise Industries]]></title>
  <link href="http://rumblesan.com/blog/categories/live-coding/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rumblesan.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-12-16T21:40:44+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://rumblesan.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[guy]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Patch-a-Day Month Day 29: A Nice Cup of Drone]]></title>
    <link href="http://rumblesan.com/blog/2010/11/29/patch-a-day-month-day-29-a-nice-cup-of-drone/"/>
    <updated>2010-11-29T22:31:22+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rumblesan.com/blog/2010/11/29/patch-a-day-month-day-29-a-nice-cup-of-drone</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I continue to wrestle somewhat with the Mandlebrot set but I don’t really feel I’m closer to getting anything useful done with it. As I couldn’t think of anything else of great use to do tonight I had another live coding practise, this time aiming for some interesting drone scapes, which I reckon I managed pretty well. I’m not really sure how much explanation I can give this tonight so I’ll talk a little bit about it and then give you the patch to play with.</p>

<p><img src="/a/2010-11-29-patch-a-day-month-day-29-a-nice-cup-of-drone/29-EveningDrone.png" alt="A drone patch done as live coding practise" /></p>

<p>Much of this is pretty rough and ready, and it’s very clear in the audio that it was clipping in lots of places. The part that helps to keep this all ticking over is the multiple sample and hold sections at the top. A single bang gets slightly delayed a few times to trigger snapshots off the same noise source. The results of this get multiplied and increased to fit into reasonable ranges and then fed to lines. The metro will cause this to trigger every four seconds and help keep things moving.</p>

<p>The squarevoice abstraction is simply a rough and ready square wave patch with a control to change the duty cycle of the wave.</p>

<p><img src="/a/2010-11-29-patch-a-day-month-day-29-a-nice-cup-of-drone/29-SquareVoice.png" alt="A squarewave voice abstraction" /></p>

<p>I also put a volume control inside to make things a little easier.</p>

<p>I’ve literally just taken a few of these and connected them together so that they intermodulate one another. There are a couple of controls for changing the frequency of some of them or the frequency of other oscillators that modulate them. I also put in two delay lines that feed signals that modulate other sections. I actually found that when i started switching parts off by setting frequencies to zero, the delay lines kept making things happen. Listen to the last minute or so of the audio to see what I mean.</p>

<p>Sound sample can be found here if the player doesn’t work.</p>

<p><a href="http://soundcloud.com/tasteforreality/cluster">http://soundcloud.com/tasteforreality/cluster</a></p>

<p>[soundcloud]<a href="http://soundcloud.com/tasteforreality/cluster">http://soundcloud.com/tasteforreality/cluster</a>[/soundcloud]</p>

<p>And the patch is available for those that want it.</p>

<p><a href="/a/2010-11-29-patch-a-day-month-day-29-a-nice-cup-of-drone/29-ChaoticTones.zip">Chaotic Drones patch</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Patch-a-Day Month Day 18: Live Coding Practise]]></title>
    <link href="http://rumblesan.com/blog/2010/11/18/patch-a-day-month-day-18-live-coding-practise/"/>
    <updated>2010-11-18T20:51:19+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rumblesan.com/blog/2010/11/18/patch-a-day-month-day-18-live-coding-practise</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So This might be a bit of a cop out but I’m currently writing this on Tuesday night under the assumption that I’m going to be busy at the pub on Wednesday evening and looking at arty things on Thursday so I’m allowing a bit of leeway due to time constraints. This evening I decided to have a go at practising some Live-Coding and realised that Once Patch-a-Day month is over, it might be a good idea to start semi regular entries on the subject, perhaps with videos as well. I’d like to do it in languages other than PureData but I’ll need some time to get up to speed with them first. Anyway, here’s a picture of the patch I constructed tonight and a bit of blurb about how it works.</p>

<p><img src="/a/2010-11-18-patch-a-day-month-day-18-live-coding-practise/16-11-2010.png" alt="Live Coding Practise 16-11-2010" /></p>

<p>The first parts to be built were the three counters in the upper left, duplicate three of them and I’ve got a sequencer of some sort to build off.</p>

<p>The contents of the click subpatch are shown at the bottom of the picture, just a noise source feeding a vcf~ object which gets triggered by a vline~. Inside the click patches there is a select that triggers of about eight numbers I picked out, roughly spread between 0 and 99. The two click patches also have slightly different frequency peaks and envelope times to get a bit more variation.</p>

<p>The third counter is controlling the drum subpatch. The sound is made by having the envelope from the vline~ control the frequency of the filter, it’s not great but it does a reasonably good job of being percussive. I need more practise at making these on the fly I think.</p>

<p>The other bits around here are some more counters which will periodically change the length of some of the first counters. It didn’t work quite as well as I’d hoped but the idea is one I’ll try to reuse.</p>

<p>The other half of the patch is two delay chains which helped to fill in quite a bit. These were simple to make and I’ll be practising making these for future use. I realised when writing this up that i should have set the values in the delwrite~ objects much higher but that’s something to remember for next time.</p>

<p>So there’s the basis of what I did. I’ll keep practising and try to find some videos of other people’s performances to show and learn from and eventually start putting my own up.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
